Okay, so we pick up in כ״ט עמוד ב׳, Kaf Tet Amud
Bet, 29B, and right at the top here, and we're dealing with
this issue about admission in front of witnesses and having to say
אתם עדי, atem edai, and then if somebody denied it, is the
person הוחזק כפרן? huchzak kafran? If the witnesses he wasn't aware of
the witnesses and then the person produced it. And the גמרא Gemara
says he's not הוחזק כפרן, huchzak kafran, he's not proven a liar,
because since he doesn't treat his admission as serious, so then it's
he doesn't remember those types of things, okay, since there was no
witnesses that were present. Okay,
but anyway, but the other point that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said is
if the person does produce witnesses that he admitted in a case
where he didn't say אתם עדי, atem edai, the person would have
to actively say משטה אני בך, meshahta ani bach, I was only
kidding. If he didn't actually say I was only kidding, we don't
say that for him. That's gets to that idea about we're not
תנינן, taninan, okay, we don't sort of argue in somebody's defense. We
saw that in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, although the ירושלמי Yerushalmi was more
prepared to do that. So now the גמרא Gemara continues like this:
ההוא דאכמין ליה עדים לחבריה בכילתא, hahu de-akhmin leh edim le-havre bi-khiltei,
four lines from the top of כ״ט עמוד ב׳. Kaf Tet Amud
Bet. ההוא דאכמין ליה עדים לחבריה בכילתא, hahu de-akhmin leh edim le-havre
bi-khiltei, somebody hid witnesses against somebody in a like a canopy bed,
okay, they were maybe behind the canopy of, you know, one of
those, what are they, you know, that's like surrounded, surrounded by a
curtain. What?
You know that famous line, the arras, behind the arras.
Oh, no, no.
Anyway, the curtains. The curtains?
Oh yeah, that like hanging, oh, well, that was that was Hamlet,
right? Yeah, yeah, yeah, he was hiding behind the curtain or whatever.
Okay. אמר ליה מן לי בידך, amar leh man li beyadkha, so
there I was and I was talking to Gloria and I said,
Gloria, you owe me a hundred dollars. אמר ליה הין, amar leh
hein, so he said yes. אמר אי בשכיבי להווי עלך סהדי, amar
ei bi-shkhivei le-havvei alakh sahadei, now, but as far as Gloria knew,
there were no witnesses around. אמר, amar, so אמר, amar, I said
to her, אי בשכיבי להווי עלך סהדי, ei bi-shkhivei le-havvei alakh sahadei,
are you prepared that everybody alive and asleep will be witnesses to
you? Okay, now as far as she knew, there was nobody there
or maybe she saw the witnesses and it looked like they were
fast asleep, okay, so, but they weren't really, they were they were
waiting to hear her admit it. And אמר ליה לא, amar leh
lo, no, I don't want anybody to be a witness for me.
So אמר רב כהנא הא אמר ליה לא, amar Rav Kahana ha
amar leh lo, so okay, even though they heard her admit it,
you know, since she since she was not basically not aware of
the witnesses and she was not saying I'm prepared to have people
serve as witnesses against me, okay, then that's not a real admission.
Okay, so funny, rather than saying that obviously she owes it and
she's trying to hide it, right, but no, we're going back to
the principle that unless basically a person says אתם עדי atem edai
or was aware of the presence of witnesses and accepts that they'll
serve as witnesses, then it is not a real admission. Okay, now
another case. ההוא דאכמין עדים בקברא לחבריה, hahu de-akhmin edim bi-khivra le-havre,
somebody went to a graveyard and had witnesses hiding in a grave,
I assume an open grave or maybe it was a mausoleum or
something. ואמר ליה מן לי בידך, ve-amar leh man li beyadkha, and
you owe me a hundred dollars. אמר ליה הין, amar leh hein,
yes. חיי ומתי להווי עלך סהדי, hayyei u-meteih le-havvei alakh sahadei, are
you prepared that the living and the dead should serve as witnesses?
Every are you prepared that everybody here and all the graves will
be witnesses? So he was trying to trick him. I can sure,
let all these dead people be witnesses against me. But אמר ליה
לא, amar leh lo, you said anybody in a grave, I had
Reuben and Simeon hiding in a grave, okay, but אמר ליה לא,
amar leh lo, no, I'm not prepared that the living and the
dead will be witnesses against me. אמר רב שמעון הא אמר ליה
לא, amar Rav Shimon ha amar leh lo, he said no. But
obviously the flip side is interesting, which means that if he said
yes, even though he didn't really see that there were witnesses, right,
I think to me the flip is interesting, right, as far as
I was concerned, you know, whatever, as far as Gloria, let's say
she was the one admitting to me, was concerned, there was nobody
around. She just thought I was סתם stam spouting nonsense when I
said you want everybody in the grave to be a witness. But
as long as she said yes and there were people in the
grave, even though she didn't see them and she wasn't maybe taking
me seriously, it sounds like that would be enough. That's אתם עדי
atem edai though. That's the אתם עדי. atem edai. I said are
you, meaning her agreeing to say, the same I would say are
you prepared for Michael and David to be witnesses and they were
standing right here and she said yes, that would be an אתם
עדי, atem edai, because meaning she doesn't have to initiate, but saying
yes is making you witnesses. Okay, so then if you guys are
hiding in a grave and I said are you prepared for everybody
in the grave to be a witness and she said yes, that
would also work. So to me, that's the bigger חידוש, chiddush, that
even in something which she could assume that I was kidding about
or whatever, wasn't taken seriously, would be binding. Okay.
And wouldn't she be taken around or she could whoever it is
in this case can turn around and say משטה? meshahta? Because like
I didn't think there was any...
משטה אני בך meshahta ani bach with the אתם עדי. atem edai.
Yeah, that's my question. It sounds like the answer is no, but
I don't understand. I mean, it's and I don't understand it. I
mean, talk about a case that's a משטה. meshahta. I don't know.
But I guess the point is once you create this formal requirement
of אתם עדי, atem edai, you know, and you don't look at
each case contextually about whether it looks like they were kidding or
not. You have to come up with formal rules. Maybe you also
allow for formal ways of satisfying those rules, you know. So okay.
Okay. Where are we? אמר
רב שמעון Amar Rav Shimon הלוואי דא, halevai da, we did this.
אמר רב ייבי ואיתימא רב פפא Amar Rav Yeivi ve-iteima Rav Papa
שמע מינה, shma mina, now this is exactly the discussion, the back
and forth I just had with Michael. From this we can infer
הדרב רב יהודה אמר רב ha-de-Rav Yehuda Amar Rav צריך לומר אתם
עדי, tzarich lomar atem edai, לא שנא כי אמר ליה לוה, lo
shna ki amar lei loveh, ולא שנא כי אמר מלוה. ve-lo shna
ki amar malveh. It doesn't matter if the one who actually owes
the money initiates and says to Michael and David, you guys be
my witnesses, or if I say, are you prepared for Michael and
David to be your witnesses? And the person says yes. Okay, because
had Gloria said yes, then you guys who were hiding in the
grave would have been the witnesses against her.
Okay,
where were we? ושתק לוה. ve-shasik loveh.
Okay. כי אמר מלוה ki amar malveh or
if I suggested it, ושתק לוה. ve-shasik loveh. And not only that,
not only if Gloria says yes, not only if I initiate and
Gloria says yes, even if I say it and she doesn't say
no, that would suffice. טעמא דאמר לוה לא, taama de-amar loveh lo,
the only reason it didn't work when you guys were hiding in
the grave and I said, are you prepared for them for those
in the grave to be witnesses, is because she said, actively said
no. אבל אי שתק, aval ei shasik, if she had not said
yes or no, and she just said, you know, then that silence
would have been like שתיקה כהודאה. shtika ke-hoda'ah. That would have counted
like admission. הכא נמי, hacha nami, that would have worked. Okay, so
this is a חידוש, chiddush, meaning and once the בבלי Bavli makes
this high demand that not only does Gloria admit it in my
presence, but Gloria also has to say אתם עדי, atem edai, where
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi we saw like things like one or the other,
either she admits it to me maybe knowing there are witnesses, or
she says אתם עדי, atem edai, if we're demanding now that you
need both, so now it seems like we're also now lowering the
criteria of what defines אתם עדי, atem edai, right? Even if you
guys are hiding and it seems, and you know, it's not, she
doesn't think I'm serious when I say that they'll be witnesses, and
even if she doesn't actively say yes, she just silently doesn't respond
to it, that also constitutes an אתם עדי. atem edai. Okay,
now where were we?
Okay. ההוא דהוי קרו ליה קב רשו. hahu de-hava karu lei kav
rashu. So there was a certain person that they called קב רשו
kav rashu which basically Rashi says what it means is is like
a bundle of like
of deeds are against him. Okay, קב, kav, you know, like a
gallon or whatever, a pound. This person has like boxes, has like
tons
of promissory notes against this person. So he had a reputation of
being deeply in debt, this person. All right, that became his nickname,
Mr. In-Debt. Okay, אמר, amar, and then this guy said, מה מסקי
בי? ma maski bi? And the person was like denying it, yeah,
it's all nonsense, who nobody has lent me money, אלא פלוני ופלוני,
ela ploni u-ploni, the only people who have ever lent me money
were Gloria and Michal. Okay, so now guess who's going to come
and ask me for money? So אתו תבעוהו לדינא. atu tav'uhu le-dina.
So now Gloria, Michal, David said, okay, at least you admitted you
owe us money. קמיה דרב נחמן. kamieh de-Rav Nachman. אמר רב נחמן
Amar Rav Nachman אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את עצמו. adam asui she-lo
le-hasbiya et atzmo. Even though I basically said that, you know, I
admitted that I owed them money. Now of course a person will
say these types of things to not make themselves look rich, you
know, which is so funny because here דוקא davka I was trying
to say I'm not in debt and nevertheless we say, but you
know, maybe you admitted that you were in debt to some people
because you don't want to look like you're too well off or
something of that nature. Now it's a little bit strange that we
give this reason, because why doesn't it just say the person never
said like אתם עדי, atem edai, right? Maybe this seems to be
explaining like why you have to say אתם עדי. atem edai. Even
if you admit you can have and maybe even in the case
like this, which and it seems this is the point of the
גמרא, Gemara, where the context makes it seem clear that the admission
is serious, okay, nevertheless, okay, if you don't say אתם עדי, atem
edai, you are not held by that admission. And we'll come up
with a reason why you have made that admission. You just don't
want to make yourself look rich or something. Again, this context doesn't
really work so well, okay, but nevertheless, that's the point. If you
didn't say אתם עדי, atem edai, the admission is not binding.
ההוא דהוה קרו ליה hahu de-hava karu lei עכברא דשכיב אדינרי, achbara
de-shachiv a-dinarei, a rat who sleeps on his piles of gold. Okay,
like a miser. He just collects all this money and he doesn't
spend it on himself and he sleeps on his piles of gold.
כי קשכיב, ki ka-shachiv, when he was dying, אמר, amar, פלוני ופלוני
מסקו בי זוזי. ploni u-ploni masku bi zuzei. You know what,
so Reuven and Shimon, they lent me money, I owe them money.
Okay, so now maybe we should say the following, you know, maybe
a deathbed admission, you know, maybe that's already something.
אמרנו אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את עצמו?
amrinu adam asui
she-lo le-hasbiya et atzmo?
Well, we haven't said that yet, we're going to say it now.
Okay, so okay,
but בתר דשכיב, batar de-shachiv, then he died. It's a little ironic,
he was שכיב אדינרי, shachiv a-dinarei, he was sleeping on, then he
was שכיב. shachiv. And now he really did. So, you know, he
can't take it with you. אתו תבעינהו ליורשין. atu tav'inehu le-yorshin. So
now they... And these ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon came and said
to the יורשים. yorshim. Now again, did he say אתם עדי? atem
edai? Did he not say אתם עדי? atem edai? Right, not clear.
Presumably, he didn't say אתם עדי. atem edai. Okay, and now we're
just sort of saying that the context doesn't get away from the
need to say אתם עדי. atem edai. אתו לקמיה דרבי שמואל בר
רבי יוסי. Atu lekamei d'Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yosi. So they came
to רבי שמואל בר רבי יוסי. Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yosi. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, he said to them, to this ראובן Reuven and
שמעון, Shimon, כי אמרינן אדם עשוי שלא להשביע את עצמו, ki amrinan
adam asuy shelo lehasbiya etzmo, הני מילי מחיים. hani mili mechayim. אבל
אחר
מיתה לא. Aval achar misah lo. So actually he said, you know
what? When somebody is alive, they'll make all different types of claims
for various reasons. On a deathbed, they're going to be honest. So
if he said it on a deathbed, presumably even without saying אתם
עדי, atem edai, that actually we will accept the deathbed admission. Okay,
and yes, you can go ahead and you can collect from the
heirs.
פרעו פלגא. Par'u palga. So the heirs paid off half the debt.
They didn't have all the money ready at once. תביעינהו לדינא לאידך
פלגא. Tavi'inhu ledina le'idach palga. So then they brought them to a
court case to try to get the other half collected. אתו לקמיה
דרבי חייא. Atu lekamei d'Rabbi Chiya. So this time, whoever it was,
רבי שמואל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yosi wasn't available,
they went to רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. Maybe not a good choice.
Go to a דיין dayan you know who rules in your favor.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said, he said, I
actually disagree with the previous פסק. psak. כשם שאדם עשוי שלא להשביע
את עצמו כך אדם עשוי שלא להשביע בניו. K'shem she'adam asuy shelo
lehasbiya etzmo, kach adam asuy shelo lehasbiya banav. The same way you
don't want to make yourself look wealthy, you don't want to make
your kids look wealthy, and maybe you admit things on a deathbed,
so everybody shouldn't try to now, you know, guy died, left over
a lot of money, everybody's going to try to take advantage of
the
kids to get the money.
Well, right. So basically what he said is, again, presumably the point
is he did not say אתם עדי. atem edai. So even a
deathbed admission without אתם עדי atem edai is not going to be
binding on the orphans. We'll say that he was saying it for
some other reason. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, so now listen, the creditors
themselves said, ניזיל ונהדר? neizal unihader?
They themselves suggested, so should we now pay the money back? Okay,
good guys, they were actually themselves offering to pay the money back.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, כבר הורה זקן. kvar hora zaken. No, because
רבי שמואל בר רבי יוסי Rabbi Shmuel bar Rabbi Yosi already פסק.
paskened. The first half that you collected was based on his פסק,
psak, okay, and that's binding. I'm not reversing it. I mean, it's
an honest debate. He פסק paskens it was a good admission, I
פסק pasken it wasn't. Okay, so that פסק psak still stands, but
for the second half, that's my case and I'm פסק paskening that
it was not a good admission. All right.
Now, הודה בפני שנים וקנו מידו. hodeh bifnei shnayim vekanu miyado. Now
let's say, okay, Gloria here admits to me in front of Michael
and David that she owes $100. Okay, and she says אתם עדי
atem edai whatever, fine. I'm now going to be able to take
that admission to court. Okay, but now what she does is she
also does a מעשה קנין, ma'aseh kinyan, right, she takes a handkerchief,
okay, and to show that you know that she's making a serious
admission. Does that empower me to get the two of you to
write a שטר? shtar? So now it's not only that I would
have to produce the two of you in court, I could get
you to write a שטר shtar that she admitted it, and then
I could just produce the שטר shtar in court and then it's
easier for her to, and then it's harder for her to deny
to say that she paid it up later because I'm still holding
on to the שטר. shtar. There's reasons why it's in my interest
to have a שטר. shtar.
Well, also נכסי דבני nichasei d'binai vs נכסי דבני חורין. nichasei d'bnei
chorin.
Yeah, but no, but that's not, no, that would only be in
the original loan. But this at least would be that I don't
have to produce you in person and that she couldn't easily claim
she paid up because I'm holding the שטר. shtar. But the שטר
shtar can only be written with the authority of the person who's
חייב. chayav.
So what's the story? כותבין. Kosevin.
So הודה בפני שנים וקנו מידו, hodeh bifnei shnayim vekanu miyado, כותבין.
kosevin. You can write a שטר. shtar. ואם לאו, Ve'im lav, but
without the קנין, kinyan, the granting of that special authority, אין כותבין,
ein kosevin, you can't write a שטר. shtar. בפני שלשה, Bifnei shlosha,
if she admitted before three people, so that's like a בית דין,
beis din, that's like we already almost had the case in court
now. If we actually had a case in court and I won
a judgment against Gloria, the court would write a שטר shtar without
Gloria's authorizing it, right? The court is writing, you know, their judgment.
So even though this isn't a court case, this is just an
admission because it's in front of three, it's like it's in front
of a court and therefore they have the authority to write the
שטר shtar but without the קנין. kinyan. So בפני שלשה ולא קנו
מידו, bifnei shlosha velo kanu miyado, at least that's the question, without
the קנין. kinyan. So רב Rav or רב אמי Rav Ami אמר
כותבין, amar kosevin, you can write a שטר, shtar, ורב אסי veRav
Assi אמר אין כותבין, ein kosevin, you can't.
הוה עובדא Hava uvda וחש ליה vechashlei רב Rav להא דרב אסי,
l'had d'Rav Assi, and רב Rav was concerned with רב אסי's Rav
Assi position not to write a שטר shtar even in front of
three without a קנין. kinyan. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava, הא אודיתא, ha odisa, now an אודיתא odisa is
an admission. Okay, it's from the word הודאה, hoda'ah, to להודות, lehodeh,
to admit. Okay, but by the way, this is very interesting in
הלכה, halacha, אודיתא odisa becomes a very big הלכתי halachic phenomenon because
basically, let's say I want to transfer my house to David. Okay,
and for whatever reason I can't do a קנין kinyan or whatever
it's difficult, okay, so what I could do is I could admit
to something that's
counterfactual. I go in front of two witnesses and I say I'm
admitting to you that David owns my house. Okay, he bought my
house from me yesterday with a קנין חזקה. kinyan chazakah. It's all
false. It never happened. But I admitted to it in front of
witnesses. So that effectively makes it happen. Okay, it creates that reality.
Okay, so anyway, that's the phrase אודיתא Odaysa becomes this vehicle that
through your admission, you can create, you can use it as a
as a way of creating new הלכה Halacha realities in the monetary
sphere by just claiming that it happened even if it didn't. But
anyway, here we're just dealing with a simple admission that I owe
somebody money, okay, and the question is about writing the שטר Shtar
or Gloria is admitting to me. הא אודיתא, Ha Odaysa, this admission,
where am I? Oh, זימנין כתבינן וזימנין לא כתבינן. Zimnin Kasvinan V'Zimnin
Lo Kasvinan.
So this issue now that we're dealing with, presumably we're dealing with
the same case, we just gave it a different name, that it
was in front of three, can the three write a שטר Shtar
or not when there was an admission? So sometimes yes, sometimes no.
It depends. What does it depend on? כניפי ויתבי, Knifi V'Yasvi, if
the three were already sitting together, they were in a bar, we
went up to them, they were gathered, לא כתבינן. Lo Kasvinan. Then
they don't have a status of a בית דין Beis Din and
just because Gloria admits to them you're not allowed to write a
שטר. Shtar. But כנפינהו איהו, Knifinhu Ihu, but let's say he went
ahead and gathered them, or Gloria went ahead, right, Gloria says, it's
not exactly clear who the איהו Ihu is. Let me see does
רש״י Rashi say who the איהו Ihu is?
No, it's not exactly clear if the איהו Ihu is me or
the איהו Ihu is Gloria. But anyway, we went and we said,
let's get three together so you can admit in front of three,
let's get these guys together. So then they were brought together to
be three. Now we could have done two, but we got three.
But we didn't do a קנין Kinyan though.
No קנין, Kinyan, but it was an admission in front of three
and the three were gathered for this purpose. That's like a בית
דין Beis Din and then you don't need a קנין Kinyan to
do a שטר. Shtar. Okay, so כתבינן. Kasvinan. רבא אמר אפילו כנפינהו
איהו, Rava Amar Afilu Knifinhu Ihu, even if they were gathered, לא
כתבינן עד דאמר להו הוו עלי דייני, Lo Kasvinan Ad D'Amar Lehu
Havu Alai Dayani, until you explicitly say serve as my judges. You
don't need a קנין, Kinyan, but Gloria has to label you like
דיינים Dayanim and that then authorizes you to write a שטר. Shtar.
מר בר רב אשי אמר אפילו אמר הוו עלי דייני, Mar Bar
Rav Ashi Amar Afilu Amar Havu Alai Dayani, even if Gloria says
be judges against me, לא כתבינן עד דקביעי דוכתא, Lo Kasvinan Ad
D'Kavi Ducha, you don't write a שטר Shtar until they really are
a court. Meaning what's a real court? It means that you have
a a place where you sit and you hear cases, ושלחו, V'Shalchu,
and you sent a a letter to bring Gloria to court, ומזמני
ליה לבי דינא, U'Mizamni Lei L'Be Dinah, and they said you got
to come to court to hear this case. Okay, which is so
funny, which is now it's not just a fiction to let you
write a שטר, Shtar, he really is saying three is never court
unless it's really a court. If you're bringing the case in front
of a court, then the court should write a שטר Shtar based
on its judgment.
But if you're not in front of a court, it's
just an admission,
unless we do a קנין, Kinyan, then you can't.
If you do a קנין, Kinyan, you can still do it. Right.
Okay, now, הודה במטלטלי וקנו מידו כותבין. Hoda B'Metaltlei V'Kanu Miyado Kasvin.
Okay, now if Gloria admitted that she owes me a chattel, hundred
dollars, whatever, then you know you need the קנין Kinyan to make
a שטר. Shtar. ואי לא אין כותבין, V'Ee Lo Ein Kasvin, which
is what we just said. במקרקעי, B'Mekarkei, but if it's land, ולא
קנו מידו, V'Lo Kanu Miyado, without a קנין, Kinyan, מה? Mah? Now
why it should be different is the following. Because land, once she
admits that it's mine, I don't have to extract it from her,
it's just there. So since it's just there, the שטר Shtar is
less as a vehicle to now bring it to court and extract,
and it's just more like just proof of what she's already admitted,
right? It's not that there's still something that's going to be being
used now to extract something. קרקע, Karka, since it's like it's just
there, she admitted it's mine, so I should be able to like
just go to it right now. Okay, so that somehow means that
you'd be more entitled to write a שטר. Shtar. Okay, so
if you look at רש״י, Rashi, he says כותבין דכיון דאודי ליה
דידיה הוא ולא מיחסר גוביינא, Kasvin Decheivan De'odi Lei Didei Hu V'Lo
Michasar Guvaya, it doesn't need to be collected. דבשלמא מטלטלי מלוה הוא
וצריך נתינה וחוב בעלמא הוא, D'Bishlama Metaltlei Milveh Hu V'Tzarich Netinah V'Chov
B'Alma Hu, it's a debt. ומלוה על פה גרע ממלוה בשטר, U'Milveh
Al Peh Garea MiMilveh B'Shtar, and there's a difference between an oral
debt and a debt with a שטר. Shtar. Debt with a שטר
Shtar is a more powerful the the
the creditor has more power. ולא ניחא ליה לאלומי, V'Lo Nicha Lei
L'Alumei,
you don't want to give me the creditor the power of having
a שטר Shtar against you. אבל הכא גילויי מילתא בעלמא הוא, Aval
Hacha Gilui Milta B'Alma Hu, here it's just proving that that this
admission was made because if it's my קרקע, Karka, it's my קרקע.
Karka. So therefore maybe you should be able to write the שטר.
Shtar. So that's the question. So so let's just finish this. במקרקעי
ולא קנו מידו מה? B'Mekarkei V'Lo Kanu Miyado Mah? אמימר אמר אין
כותבין, Amemar Amar Ein Kasvin, you still don't write it. מר זוטרא
אמר כותבין, Mar Zutra Amar Kasvin, you write it. והלכתא כותבין, V'Hilchasa
Kasvin, and the הלכה Halacha is you write it. And now one
case, רבינא איקלע לדהמריא. Ravina Ikla L'Dihamarya.
And why is that?
Because for what we just said, it's not like a different type
of a loan, it's there was an admission made, it's mine, and
it's just proof.
But we didn't say that with מטלטלי Metaltlei though.
Right, because מטלטלי Metaltlei you have to extract, the case isn't over.
רבינא איקלע לדהמריא, Ravina Ikla L'Dihamarya, רבינא Ravina came to this place
דהמריא. Damarya. אמר ליה רב דימי בר רב הונא מדהמריא, Amar Lei
Rav Dimi Bar Rav Huna MiDamarya, this רב דימי בר רב הונא
Rav Dimi Bar Rav Huna of this place said to רבינא, Ravina,
מטלטלי ואיתנהו בעיניהו מה? Metaltlei V'Isnehu B'Eineihu Mah? That's fine, that's if
Gloria owes me money, writing a שטר Shtar makes it a different
type of debt. Let's say however, that I prove that Gloria admits
that the car she has in her front yard is my car.
Okay, it's an actual concrete thing. So that's not like a debt.
debt, maybe that should be like קרקע, Karka, maybe we should be
able to write a שטר Shtar there. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, כקרקע
דמי, KeKarka Dami, that is like קרקע Karka and you can write
a שטר. Shtar. רב אשי Rav Ashi disagrees. רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi Amar, כיון דמחסרי גוביינא, Keivan DeMechassrei Guvaina, no, קרקע Karka you
just walk into it. Here, even though it's a concrete thing, I'd
have to get her to deliver that car to me. So no,
it is not like a, it's like, it's not like קרקע Karka
and you do not write a שטר Shtar unless you're explicitly empowered
to write a שטר. Shtar. Okay? So we'll stop right here and
we will pick up with this tomorrow.